Finding Aid for Delta Omega. Delta Chapter (University of Michigan) records, 1925-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Delta Omega. Delta Chapter (University of Michigan) records 1925-1971
Delta Omega. Delta Chapter (University of Michigan).
0.4 linear foot
87386 Bn 2
Honorary public health society. Historical information, minutes, financial material, constitution and by-laws, membership material, and papers presented at annual initiation banquets.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Delta Chapter (Donor No. 5165 ) in October 1971.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Delta Omega Society was founded at the School of Hygiene and Public Health of Johns Hopkins University in 1924 by Major Edgar Erskine Hume of the Medical Corps, U.S. Army and Past Assistant Surgeon Claude William Mitchell. The organization was created to be a national honorary public health fraternity with the purpose of recognizing and encouraging scholarship and research by graduate students in public health. The society also sought to honor those public health professionals who possessed exceptional qualifications or who had achieved prominence in the field.
The Delta Chapter of the Delta Omega Society was founded at the University of Michigan's School of Public Health in 1925. Like the national organization, the Delta Chapter existed to honor those public health students who had worked hard to deserve distinction. Since the national society sought to serve as an honorary society, the Delta Chapter concentrated its activities on selecting and initiating members from the University's public health program. The culminating event of the chapter's activities rested in the Initiation Banquet at which a public health professional would present a paper on some topic relating to the field.
The ranks of Delta Omega expanded over the years with yearly initiations of between 10 and 20 new members. The Chapter was deactivated in July 1971.
These organizational records consist of the following six series: Historical Information; Minutes; Financial; By-Laws; Membership/Officers; and Annual Initiation Banquets.
Subjects:
Delta Omega. Delta Chapter (University of Michigan); Public health--United States.; University of Michigan--Honorary societies.
- Historical Information/Publications
  Historical Information (1 folder; 1942-1951) consists of two publications of the Delta Omega Society. The first, written in 1942, is a publication of the national organization which provides background information about the development of the society. The second publication was done by the Delta Chapter in 1957 to describe its function and history.
  - The Delta Omega Society, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Delta Omega, 1951 (Box 1)
- Minutes
  Minutes (6 folders; 1925-1971 scattered) include the written records of various committee meetings. The first type of minutes consists of a fairly complete record of the annual meetings (1925-1971). The first part includes both semi-annual and annual meeting minutes. After 1947, only annual meeting minutes were kept. Also included in this series are business meeting minutes covering the time periods 1952-1955 and 1960-1964. This committee discussed financial transactions and plans. Minutes from the Executive Council covering 1959-1961 discuss administrative details. The Policy Committee dealt with procedural issues with the records representing 1950-1957. The final type of minutes has been labelled Miscellaneous and represents one record from 1951 for the following committees: Constitution and By-Laws, Membership, and Program and Publicity.
  - 1925-1947 (Semiannual/annual meetings) (Box 1)
  - 1947-1971 (Annual Meetings) (Box 1)
  - 1952-1964 (scattered dates) (Business Meetings) (Box 1)
  - 1959-1961 (Executive Council Meetings) (Box 1)
  - 1950-1957 (Policy Committee) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Constitution and By-Laws Committee, February 19, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Membership Committee, January 30, 1951 and March 6, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Program and Publicity Committee, January 10, 1951 (Box 1)
- Annual Financial Records
  Financial Records (1 folder; 1925-1971 scattered) consists of annual summaries of finances from 1925 through 1971. The summaries are one-page documents which list the amounts of money taken in from membership dues and spent on various events and supplies.
  - 1925-1971 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
- By-Laws
  By-Laws (1 folder; scattered dates) consist of several revisions of the rules that governed the Chapter as adopted and from the national organization.
  - 1952, 1958, 1960, 1968 (Box 1)
- Membership
  Membership/Officers (2 folders; 1928-1968) contains lists of members, both faculty and students. The membership lists of varying completeness cover 1928 to 1968 while the lists of officers run from 1940 to 1968.
  - Member listings, 1928-1968 (Box 1)
  - Officers, 1940-1968 (Box 1)
- Annual Initiation Banquets
  Annual Initiation Banquets (3 folders; 1940-1970) reflect the culminating event of the year for the Chapter. The programs show the members initiated at each banquet from 1940 to 1969. The papers are copies of the presentations at each banquet by a public health professional.
  - Programs, 1940-1969 (Box 1)
  - Annual Lectures, 1944-1970 (scattered dates)
    - 1944, "Public Health as an International Problem" (Box 1)
    - 1951, "Rice as a Factor in Asiatic Diets" (Box 1)
    - 1952, "The Misery of Man and What to Do About It" (Box 1)
    - 1954, "Epidemiological Techniques and Data in Public Health Planning" (Box 1)
    - 1955, "Interrelation Between Public Health and Medical Care, 1750-1950" (Box 1)
    - 1956, "The Effect of Cultural Factors Upon Health Problems" (Box 1)
    - 1957, "Problems in Adult Immunization" (Box 1)
    - 1958, "World-Wide Malaria Eradication" (Box 1)
    - 1960, "The Population Explosion" (Box 1)
    - 1961, "Public Health Significance of Aeroallergens" (Box 1)
    - 1962, "The Changing World of Health" (Box 1)
    - 1963, "Public Health: the Art of the Possible" (Box 1)
    - 1964, "Public Health Program Planning for the Future" (Box 1)
    - 1965, "Total Action Against Poverty More than a Name" (Box 1)
    - 1966, "Social Policy for Health: the Heart, Cancer, Stroke Controversy" (Box 1)
    - 1967,"Health Planning on a Community Basis" (Box 1)
    - 1969, "Transmission of Viral Diseases by Drinking Water" (Box 1)
    - 1970, "Community and the Public's Health" (Box 1)
- Realia
  - Fraternity pin with photograph (Box 1)